Guide to the Henry Marie Brackenridge and Family Papers, 1816-1889 DAR.1937.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Brackenridge Family Correspondence, 1821-1857; II.
  This series contains letters written by or sent to Brackenridge family members. The majority of the letters are written by H.M. Brackenridge to his wife, Caroline Marie Brackenridge, during long periods of separation. The letters make numerous references to their fluctuating moods and various illnesses, including depression. The letters dealing with Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge, H.M. Brackenridge's son, concern his education as well as his health. Much of the correspondence written to H.M. Brackenridge served to keep him informed of the activities of his family and friends while he traveled. There are also letters written by H.M. Brackenridge's sister, Cornelia and his brothers, Alexander and William. Cornelia's letters are particularly enlightening about social activities and include suggestions of suitable women for marriage. Represented as well are letters from cousins John Cabell and Robert Breckinridge. There are also letters written to Caroline and Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge from several of their friends. The letters are arranged into groups, according to family member. Letters between family members are grouped according to the writer.
  The order of these documents from the letter book has been noted through the inclusion of a letter book number (e.g. LB#01). See custodial history for more information.
  - Alexander Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 52), October 23, 1818 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Alexander, writing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, discusses a new edition of Modern Chivalry. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - Alexander Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 66), January 8, 1827 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Alexander, writing from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, speaks of family matters. He also praises H. M. Brackenridge's speech delivered about Thomas Jefferson and John Adams. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge to Samuel A. Rulon, May 5, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Benjamin Morgan, writing from Tarentum, Pennsylvania, to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, describes a difficult trip across Pennsylvania, during which there was an accident going up an inclined plane. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge from Samuel A. Rulon, (LB# 59), December 24, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Rulon, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, shares news of mutual friends. Rulon mentions that the celebration of a friend's birthday lasted until 11 o'clock, a time he thought "was rather late hours for Quakers." 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge, July 5, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Benjamin Morgan, writing from Niagara Falls, New York, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, thanks his father for the money sent to him and describes the beauty of the falls and his adventures while there.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge from Rachel C. Smith, (LB# 6), October 16, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This letter was sent with a Bible from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge from John W. Rulon, (LB# 7), December 18, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Rulon, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, relays the wishes of Benjamin Morgan's mother concerning her clothing and personal belongings. [The letter was written soon after Caroline's death in 1852.] 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge to Phillipine Brackenridge, February 6, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Writing during a stay in New York, New York, Benjamin Morgan recounts a recent illness and describes a ball which he attended. He offers his opinion on the clothing of others who were in attendance. 4 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge from Margaret Ann Overton, April 28, 1830 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Margaret Ann Overton, writing from Pensacola, Florida, to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, speaks of efforts to raise money for a church. She also notes H. M. Brackenridge's return to Florida. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge, February 5, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    In this letter from May Pleasant, Pennsylvania, Caroline requests H. M. Brackenridge to send word about their impending trip to Washington, D.C. She complains of her weak nerves, lack of appetite and insomnia. She also fears that Benjamin Morgan might be contracting the measles from the children of the family with whom they are visiting. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge to Mary Weaver, March 18, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Caroline, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Freeport, Pennsylvania, apologizes for not previously sending a letter from Washington, D.C., as she was unable to make the journey. She relays that she has been sick most of the winter and that Morgan has the mumps. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge, October 12, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Caroline, writing from Tarentum, Pennsylvania, to Washington, D.C., provides an update on domestic matters and informs H. M. Brackenridge of her travel plans. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge from Mrs. M. L. Alexander, June 9, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Alexander, writing from Washington, D.C., to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, offers news of a boarding house in which she and Caroline used to live. 4 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge from Lydia Burrough, 1842-1845 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Burrough, writing from the Philadelphia area, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, describes in this series of letters two of their mutual friends' deaths and the events leading up to them. She also details the condition of various family members and their travels around the East Coast.
  - Caroline Brackenridge from A.B. and J. W. Rulon, September 27, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    The Rulons, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, inform Caroline about a potential visit the following summer. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge from R. Fletcher, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Fletcher, writing from West Chester, Pennsylvania to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, speaks of a nephew who is planning to visit Caroline and her family. Fletcher also describes family matters and recent activities. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Caroline Brackenridge to Miss Louisa Weaver, April 13, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Caroline, writing from Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, to Lancaster, Pennsylvania, offers an account of how her winter was spent. She spent four weeks in Philadelphia, prior to going to Harrisburg. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 55), November 24, 1816 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Cornelia, writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, chides her brother for not writing. She also mentions various family friends. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 54), March 17, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Cornelia, writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, mentions Miss Mary Hamilton, a woman she thinks H. M. Brackenridge should consider marrying. She also laments her lack of free time. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 69), May 30, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, Cornelia speaks of H. M. Brackenridge's book on the history of the War of 1812. She offers her opinion on H. M. Brackenridge's marital status. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 70), August 16, 1819 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, Cornelia expresses her wish to receive a visit from H. M. Brackenridge. Also provided are updates on friends and family. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 63), January 26, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Cornelia, writing to Annapolis, Maryland, describes a trip to Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, where she stayed at the Governor's Mansion. She recounts a speech she heard their brother Alexander give. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 24), March 15, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Cornelia, writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, discusses family matters and relays information about mutual friends. She also offers her opinion on two local women as potential wives for her brother. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 58), June 23, 1820 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Cornelia, writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, speaks of being sick for several months and a visit to Mr. Ramsay's sulfur springs. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - Cornelia Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge, May 18, 1821 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Writing from Carlisle, Pennsylvania to Pensacola, Florida, Cornelia chastises her brother for not keeping in touch. She mentions Alexander's current interests in traveling. She also requests an update from H. M. Brackenridge concerning his travels. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge (LB # 58), December 30, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    H. M. Brackenridge, writing from Washington D.C., to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, expresses the importance of learning the fundamentals of education. He also describes the state of fashion in the nation's capital. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge, January 29, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    H. M. Brackenridge, writing from Washington D.C., to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, recounts different speakers he has heard in front of the House of Representatives, including Henry Clay and Daniel Webster. He also includes a math problem for his son to complete. 3 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge, February 5, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    H. M. Brackenridge writes to discourage a trip to visit Washington, D. C., which was planned for Benjamin Morgan and Caroline. He thinks the chaos of the city will be bad for Caroline's nerves. He also mentions a cabinet filled with stones he bought for his son. 2 p. A.L.S.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, January - July 1827 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    In this series of letters, mostly from Florida, H. M. Brackenridge notes his desire to be able to spend more time with Caroline. He includes some description of life in Florida, including a lengthy account of a local murder, and the death of a friend's young son. He also offers advice related to matters of health.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, August - November 1827 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    In this group of letters, H. M. Brackenridge describes the difficulties of living in Florida. Fever is rampant and has claimed several friends. He often expresses his desire to leave Florida, but admits reluctance to forfeit his position. Most of the letters were sent from various locations in Florida. Several were written during the arduous trip between Florida and Pennsylvania. Of much concern to H. M. Brackenridge is finding a boarding house where he and Caroline can find some privacy. Caroline's mental state is another recurring topic. H. M. Brackenridge worries about her aversion to meeting new people.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, January - June 1828 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Some of these letters were sent during a sea voyage H. M. Brackenridge embarked upon during a return trip to Florida. The rest were written in various locations in Florida. Topics discussed in this series of correspondence include the sale of land in Florida, opinions on several acquaintances, and the strain of living far from Pennsylvania.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, July - December 1828 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    These letters were all sent from various locations in Florida. H. M. Brackenridge wrote of plans to return to Pennsylvania for the summer, the weather, and financial matters. He also mentions having written to Andrew Jackson concerning an appointment in Pittsburgh. The health of Caroline and Benjamin are recurring concerns in these letters.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, January - May 1829 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    H. M. Brackenridge wrote these letters from Florida. He describes plans for a house to be built along the Allegheny River, Benjamin's health problems, and his property in Florida.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, June - November 1829 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    These letters were written from a variety of locations during a trip to the north H. M. Brackenridge took via river boat. Several letters were sent from Washington, D.C., and convey his thoughts on corruption in the Jackson administration. H. M. Brackenridge suspects that several acquaintances had recently lost their positions to political allies of the administration and wonders if this fate awaits him as well. Also noted are H. M. Brackenridge's repeated attempts to meet with Jackson and the Secretary of the Navy.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, February - July 1830 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    This series of letters was written from Florida and is filled with references to various acquaintances, health concerns, and descriptions of life in Florida. H. M. Brackenridge often relates advice on how to properly raise Benjamin. Also described is the condition of the orange trees on his land.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, August - December 1830 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    H. M. Brackenridge sent these letters from several different towns in Florida. Included are updates on the construction of his house in Tarentum, thoughts on parenting, and preparations for a trip north.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, January - May 1831 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    H. M. Brackenridge wrote most of these letters during a trip from Florida to Pennsylvania. They discuss preparations for inhabiting the newly built house in Tarentum, Pennsylvania.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, June - December 1831 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    H. M. Brackenridge sent these letters from Florida, mainly from Pensacola. They cover real estate matters, concerns for the health of his family, and future plans.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, 1832-1835 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    In this collection of letters, H. M. Brackenridge discusses the termination of his position by Andrew Jackson and life in Tarentum, Pennsylvania.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Caroline Brackenridge, 1841-1843 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    These letters were written when H. M. Brackenridge was in Washington D.C., during his time as a U.S. representative. H. M. Brackenridge writes of life in Washington D.C., and his activities in Congress.
  - H. M. Brackenridge to Henry Morgan and Cornelia C. Brackenridge, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    H. M. Brackenridge explains to his grandchildren his wishes concerning the use of a spring on family land. H. M. Brackenridge also recounts a speech he gave on the occasion of the deaths of Thomas Jefferson and John Adams. 4 p. A.L.S.
  - John Cabell Breckinridge to H. M. Brackenridge, December 1853 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Breckinridge, writing from Washington, D.C., to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, mainly discusses their common ancestry. [ Vice President Breckinridge, in the Buchanan administration and a general in the Confederate army, was the grandson of Hugh Henry Brackenridge's brother.] 4 p. A.L.S.
  - Robert Jefferson Breckinridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 116), March 13, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Breckenridge, writing from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Tarentum, Pennsylvania, outlines a plan for a "civilized state in the tropiks" and another for "universal freedom." He also mentions the common origin of both of their families. 1 p. A.L.S.
  - William H. Brackenridge to H. M. Brackenridge (LB # 41), May 13, 1819 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    William, writing from Indiana, Pennsylvania, to Baltimore, Maryland, informs H. M. Brackenridge that he will seek subscriptions for H. M. Brackenridge's projected history of South America. He also notes his dislike for politicians. 3 p. A.L.S.
- Henry Marie Brackenridge Speeches and Essays, 1818-1864, III.
  The secries of the collection contains a sample of H.M. Brackenridge's essays and speeches. H.M. Brackenridge was a prolific writer whose articles were printed in a number of different publications. The articles are a mix of book reviews, biographies, political essays, and travel accounts, which reflects H.M. Brackenridge's varied interests. Editorial notes are included in the margins, suggesting that H.M. Brackenridge continued to rework his writings after their publication. Many of the speeches were given in various towns in western Pennsylvania on the occasion of the 4th of July. The dated works in this collection cover a period of four decades, from 1818 to 1864, though some of the material is undated. The collection also contains some political essays and speeches commenting on his career and disagreeing with contemporary political movements. [Please note that folders 1-9 contain the various essays written by H.M. Brackenridge, and folders 10-17 contain his speeches.]
  - Review of "Life of General Harrison", 1839 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    This folder contains some of H. M. Brackenridge's published works, along with comments written in the margins. Topics include the life of William Henry Harrison, the history of the Federalist party, and the political career of Martin Van Buren.
  - "Uncle Tom's Cabin", 1852 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Contains both a handwritten draft and a published version (in the form of a newspaper clipping) of H. M. Brackenridge's essay about the Harriet Beecher Stowe abolitionist novel.
  - "A Remarkable Journey from Philadelphia in Twelve Days in 1832", undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    This travel account seems to have been intended as an appendix to one of the public letters addressed to Andrew Jackson after H. M. Brackenridge's dismissal as judge in Florida. It recounts a rushed trip H. M. Brackenridge embarked upon in order to attend a court date.
  - "Examination into the Boundaries of Louisiana", undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    This essay provides both a detailed history of European settlement in Louisiana, as well as a geographical description of the area. 25 p.
  - Newspaper Essay Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    This is one of the editorials H. M. Brackenridge wrote concerning Andrew Jackson. H. M. Brackenridge's handwritten comments are also included.
  - Review of Craig's History, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Newspaper clippings of several reviews H. M. Brackenridge wrote of Nelville Craig's book about the history of Pittsburgh.
  - Review of "Florida Affairs", undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Newspaper clippings of several editorials written by H. M. Brackenridge.
  - Review of "Scenes of Childhood", undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Contained within is a newspaper article detailing H. M. Brackenridge's childhood years.
  - "The Independence of the Judiciary", undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    A lengthy draft, with editorial comments by H. M. Brackenridge written in the margins. Includes criticisms of the Jackson administration. 38 p.
  - Speech on the Jew Bill, 1818 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    This is a copy of a speech given by H. M. Brackenridge to the Maryland House of Delegates. Also included is a copy of an exchange between H. M. Brackenridge and John Young on the topic. 7 p.
  - Fourth of July Oration-- Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 1835 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    H. M. Brackenridge's speech focuses on the shortcomings of Andrew Jackson. Also included are his thoughts on the history of the Democratic and Federalist parties. 17 p.
  - Fourth of July Oration-- Freeport, Pennsylvania, 1838 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Handwritten copy of a speech given by H. M. Brackenridge. In the speech, H. M. Brackenridge recounted the founding of the United States and voiced criticisms of the current state of politics. 20 p.
  - "Stump Speech", September 1840 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Copy of a speech, with H. M. Brackenridge's corrections. The speech details economic problems and the rise of central banking in the United States. 14 p.
  - Speech on the Treasury Note Bill, February 3, 1841 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Printed copy of a speech given to the House of Representatives, explaining H. M. Brackenridge's dissatisfaction with the Treasury Note Bill. Though the country had serious financial troubles, H. M. Brackenridge thought the problems could be solved without the use of Treasury notes. 16 p.
  - Fourth of July Oration-- Tarentum, Pennsylvania, 1844 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    In this speech, H. M. Brackenridge reflected upon the principles on which the United States was founded. He also described the history of the United States and Great Britain. 8 p.
  - "Argument before the Supreme Court", October 8, 1849 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Published account of H. M. Brackenridge's speech. The case revolved around the question of whether or not vacant land could be employed for public use. 22 p.
  - "Protest of Henry Marie Brackenridge against the Bounty Tax", 1864 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    An essay on a tax concerning residents of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania. 1 p.
- Miscellaneous Items, 1857-1889; IV.
  The personal papers of H.M. Brackenridge are an assortment of documents including copies, presumably in his hand, of several literary works of popular authors (although one is dated after his death and may have been copied by another family member). The papers include obituary notices for H.M. Brackenridge and his daughter-in-law, Phillipine Brackenridge and guardianship papers for the children of Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge. This series also includes a clarinet that belonged to Brackenridge.
  - Case of H. M. Brackenridge vs. John Wineman, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Guardianship Papers of Benjamin Morgan Brackenridge, December 1863 - February 1864 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Historical Society of Wisconsin Membership Certificate, June 30, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Memorandum Books, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Obituary Notice for H. M. Brackenridge, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Receipt, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - H. M. Brackenridge's Translation of The Sick Prisoner, by Maroncelli, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Obituary Notice for Phillipine Brackenridge, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Miscellany, A Scene from "William Tell" (LB# 65), March 26, 1872 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Miscellany, Threnody on the Death of a Child (LB# 64), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Letter in German, 1854 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Clarinet, undated (Oversize 1)